okay okay okay so today we're gonna be
sharing the screen okay sure screen sure
boom and here we go alright so
foundations of deep learning that's me
follow me on Twitter
yay of course okay so today we're going
to be talking about attention and
specifically there are two types of
attention there is self attention or
cross attention and there's going to be
also heart attention or soft attention
okay but in generally generally when we
talk about attention we're gonna be
talking about dealing with sets
so since I'm gonna give you a small
preview Transformers are made of
attention modules transformers are going
to be something that Maps sets to sets
they don't really deal with sequences
they can write a sequence can be thought
as a order set but they don't
necessarily need to have order sequences
that's the super cool part all right so
let's get started let's think let's
start first with self attention so we
have like a set of X's this my pink axis
which are X subscript I with I goes from
1 to T right so you have T different
elements in this set X 1 X 2 blah blah
blah XT so now we can think about each
of these X is is belonging to RN right
that's our classical representation we
have seen so far right so it's like n
dimensional vector so all there is to
this self attention is that my H my
hidden representation is going to be a
linear combination of these vectors
right and so I guess if you remember
from one of the classes early on like I
think the fourth class I show you how
you can do like a quick way like a quick
notation for a right in this
linear combination of vectors rain and
it's simply by using matrix
multiplication so this set of X's which
are T exists in dimension n can be
thought as a matrix capital X in pink
that has n rows no because the height of
these guys are n and then has T columns
right so you can think about that is
basically the stack the horizontal stack
of these vectors right so this is my set
in which again you have an order right
now
and so now this hidden representation
can be written as what the matrix x
times the vector of those alphas which
I'm going to be calling a in a bold bold
typeset okay so in this case my H is the
X matrix times a it's a bit funky right
usually when we think about the hidden
representation we have a rotation of my
input right with the weight matrix but
in this case is like huh what is this is
the rotation of the attention so it
doesn't kind of I can't really think
that way so I prefer to think about this
as you know the linear combination of
these columns of X range so the linear
combination of those X is cool so we can
write it there top right just to keep it
in in memory right now we can think
about hard attention if we impose that
the zero norm of these a vector it's
equal one and the nonzero term equal one
as well so which means a is a one hot
encoded vector and therefore what has
happen if you multiply these x times a
one hot vector you can select the you
know the specific where the one is
there's going to be that specific column
right so if the second element of a is
equal one and all the others are zero
when you multiply a capital X time
which is 0-1 or later or the others are
zero you can adjust retrieve the column
second column right so you can see now
how this can work out right so this
attention just pays attention to one
element of your set and one element only
in the case that we are when we are
talking about heart attention but we can
also have a different attention which is
the soft attention in the soft attention
instead the constraint is that the
summation of these elements all by a the
alphas they have to sum to one okay so
that's the difference
and in this case H is going to be just
you know a dinner combination of these
the columns of the matrix capital X
right so far could rain there is no
we're stuff right okay so second part
attention number two we're gonna figure
out where these a is coming from right
and so in this case a as I as you can
figure out is going to be the arc max or
the soft dark max of these capital X
where I transpose it so that you mean
every row is one sample and then I
compute the scalar product between the
the row and the vector let every element
in the final product every element is
going to be the scalar product of each
and every you know a vector X I that was
from 1 to T against these specific X
okay but so is it is it clear so far
so before we said what's beta beta is
the parameter for the soft arc max write
the inverse of the temperature whenever
you know soft dark mass right the expo
of the argument divided by the sum of
the X and then inside the X we have beta
right where does beta come from yeah and
that's the whenever you have these soft
arc max or what people call soft max
there is always a beta parameter usually
it's set to 1 so you don't see it
so before we saw that
my capital X okay I didn't okay I didn't
talk about yet so the big eggs right big
X is this set of columns Tata Tata Tata
and then the H is gonna be a linear
combination of these columns but where
are these alphas coming from right and
so my given alpha my first vector a is
going to be you know each and every
basically column of X so which means
every row in the X transpose u
multiplied by X right and you get the
scalar product of these two guys so you
get how much my X what is the value of
the scalar product of my X against every
other value every other X in my set okay
is X a column of vector
yeah X is one vector size n okay this
like it was written before X is a
generic X right so my square bracket
represents a optional argument so you
can have either the Arg max and
therefore you get a one hot a or if you
have this soft arcamax which is the the
one that we've been using all the course
so far you are going to get the
exponential divided by the summation of
the old exponential right that's the
classical one that the one that people
call softmax usually all right so but
then we said that we have a set of X's
right so if you have a set of X's these
will imply that you have a set of AIDS
right because for every X you're gonna
have an A and so if you have these many
aids that are vectors right you can
stack them one after each other tan-tan
tan tan-tan and you get capital A and so
capital a it's gonna have the height
it's gonna be of size T right because
the size T so you know the lowercase a
has size T just because you're gonna
have T rose in X transpose right and
then you stuck T's of them right because
you have T X's
I hope it's clear and so far all right
cool know what's missing right now so
what's missing is the following so given
it now we have a set of the AIDS
therefore you're gonna have a set of
ages right if you see from the top right
side of this slide you have H was this
you know matrix multiplication between
the capital X and the a right so H was
the linear combination of the columns of
my X matrix right but given that we have
many aids we are going to end up with
many ages right so how many H is the
same number of A's right and so you're
gonna have these capital X matrix which
is gonna have many many columns right
hey sorry so small X in the soft max
equation that belongs to our end right
that's one of the one of the columns of
X yeah yeah so I would you can call that
X I and I would have a would be a I
right about I remove the index so it
becomes a bit less cluttered okay but so
X is T by n right so X transpose should
be n by T so X is going to be n by T
grain Oh X is n by T also X is gonna be
the the stack of all these columns one
of three at each other right okay yeah I
saw there are two options you can think
about X being the the set of rows and
this I think what's done usually in code
but I think this is much easier to write
down in this way if you write the math I
mean I prefer okay and so again given
that we have many AIDS you're gonna have
many columns of the H matrix right and
so we can simply write that my capital H
which is the subset of these H's is
going to be the linear combination of
this element of X
using the factors like in the first
column of a and the second column of a
third column right so that was pretty
much it about attention so you basically
mix the components of this set of X's
which we can represent as a matrix by
using these coefficients that are
computed by using the Arg max of the
soft argh max where each component
inside we can call this stuff inside
here a score it's simply the scalar
product of 1 given X against all the
sets of my exes ok so this is the first
part of the lecture it should be clear
until here otherwise we can move forward
so is it clear so far or is not
explained the first equation again for
one what is soft Arg max and value a
multiplying big eggs with eggs right so
in the in the previous slide we simply
said there is one line only here
basically and we say that the hidden
layer it's gonna be a linear combination
of these X's right yes and this in a
combination is using these alphas which
is contained in this vector a yes and so
I wrote this one here right so H is
gonna be the linear combination of the
columns of the X where the column of X
is gonna be the elements in my set yes
ok so if we got this one we go to the
second slide and I tell you how to
compute one a ok so to compute one a
here this one a is going to be for
example the soft dark max which is again
people call the soft max of what so you
have a specific X here right when you
compute the product between these X
transpose X transpose is gonna have all
those X's in rows right so let me draw
this one right so X transpose gonna have
like first simple second guy
third guy right and then I do this one
against my guy here right so if you do
matrix vector multiplication the first
item is going to be this color scalar
product of the first guy against myself
then the second guy against myself and
the third guy against myself right then
I'm you get here for example three
scores right you're gonna see how close
how aligned basically your vector is
with respect to the three items in my
set and then I around the soft Arg max
right so I get these three values you
get at the end one value two second
value third value at the end is gonna
sum to one right yes I'll talk about it
it's not sure and you can have either
one you can have the soft calc max you
have the exponents of blah blah blah or
you can get the arc max right and you
get which is basically sending the beta
to very large values right so you can
just simply writes off target max and
have large beta I'm still confused why
is this a vector in R T which on line
defining a yes army okay
so X transpose is gonna be my axis right
direction right so this guy here is my X
transpose
okay
and this length here this is gonna be N
and this is gonna be T so if you do T
times this guy which is also n right
you're gonna get a vector of
steep right
does it make spell though is a are one
hot batter a can be a one hot if you use
arc Max or is going to be you know a
softer version if you use this soft dark
max right which is the X divided by the
sum of the X prime well when you
multiply a matrix by a vector you get a
vector so if you're taking an arm R max
over that you should get a scaler no no
the Arg max is gonna give you the index
ring like the one hot vector
corresponding to the the vector you can
think about art mass art max is giving
you like a one where you have the
maximum and all the rest are going to be
0 okay yeah does it make sense oh yeah
so if you have like 3 7 9 to a vector of
for the arc max you can give you 0 0 1 0
no it's gonna give you the one at the
position where the maximum is okay all
right well it's beta Skyler right now
you can think is that being equal to 1
there is no need here oh this one right
now okay for a little bit of additional
certification is our the X terms are
those are those one hot vectors that
represent our like our input X eyes are
sorry X eyes are just my input doesn't
have to be one hot
but they could be if they represent
words or no I think they are usually
they are embeddings so they are actually
dense so I don't think they're okay then
the X transpose by X is that kind of
multiplying that's that's determining
the similarity between okay so this is
determining how similar each element in
my set of X's it's similar to my X right
so this a tells me how these all of
these guys here are similar with respect
to this guy over here okay I think cool
cool cool
all right so this was the first part
let's move on and see how these can be
improved and like expanded
so here we have a definition the key
value store this is about data structure
just to give you a little bit of
definition right so this is a paradigm
for storing saving retrieving Aquarion
or managing an associative array or a
dictionary or a hash table what does it
mean so for example you want to type
some you know question on like let's say
you want to check a video about how to
make a lasagna on YouTube okay so you're
going YouTube you write lasagna lasagna
whatever you press enter so you have a
query and then the query is gonna be
checking against all possible keys in
your data set and the keys could be like
the title of the video or the
description right and so you check how a
line is your query against all those
titles that are available in the YouTube
data set right when you find the maximum
matching score you can retrieve that one
right so if you do the arc max you just
retrieve one video otherwise if you do
these soft arc max you can get basically
a probability distribution right and
then you can do retrieve in order right
you can retrieve first the most aligned
video that you have you know you can
have a sequence of less and less
relevant videos right so is it clear so
far about what is this key value store
paradigm right so you just have a query
which is your question given one query
you check all the keys and you can find
how matching the key is with respect to
your query and then you retrieve all
those videos all those values right all
those content so we're gonna do exactly
the same here
in in this case right so we're gonna be
specializing a little bit what we have
seen so far which was pretty you know
trivial the key here would be the title
of the video yeah that's correct right
so the keys are the title of all the
videos in YouTube you have one query
lasagna okay
how to cook lasagna is I've and I you
check this question against all the keys
and then when you find you know the art
max you find the index of the highest
you retrieve that one right or again if
you do the soft dark max you're gonna
get like probabilities now you can sort
by probability for example right so we
have now queries keys and values so what
are these well these are simply rotation
all my specific input X right so my Q is
going to be getting my X here I rotate
it by W Q then my key is going to be
again my X I rotated by W of K and then
I have my value of V sorry I'm gonna be
rotating the X by a WV okay so so far we
just added three matrices more and at it
so this is like how you can you know add
so much more well we finally add some
training parameters right so so far we
didn't have any training board
parameters so far what would be D would
be X in the lasagna metaphor X is me
very hungry and so me very hungry and
goes and try to write some question
about how to get the food done okay but
then given that I also know how to cook
I can also check against all okay there
you go
right so the the about cooking lasagna
all right so I'm hungry and it would be
my hacks X so my query would be what is
the best recipe I can find and then I
can check in my memory right in my own
head all the possible lasagna recipes I
have all my mother's cookbook right so I
can check check check check check and I
saw my grandmother lasagna and then I
retrieved the recipe from my granny
which is you know amazing makes sense
right I'm hungry
there a reason why we don't add
nonlinearities here yeah yeah so this is
just these attention thing it's
completely based on orientation right
we're gonna just check in what is the
orientation of these vectors so this is
how attention works okay we don't like
nonlinearities the only non-linearity is
whenever you try to get the probability
you know distribution right the the soft
dark max make sense okay cool
all right so you're on board so again we
first now introduce these learning
parameters such that we can train
something right machine learning yay
okay so Q and K have to have the same
length right the same dimensionality
because you're gonna check one query one
question how to make lasagna against all
the possible representation of the
titles right so they have to have the
same length because otherwise you can't
check the orientation right it'd have to
be in the same space V that's V is the
content of my recipe right I don't care
about the length it can be you know five
pages of my of the recipe right so it's
just you know that's the whole recipe
right so V in my case is huge and the
key is the representation of the title
which match the size of the
representation of the question right
cool let's make things you know simple
and down bend down everything we just
said D prime equal D second equal to D
right so everything is just D all right
so we said we have a sequence we know
sequence right and if I'm wrong we have
a set of X's right so given that we have
a set of X's therefore you're gonna get
a set of queries you get a set of keys
and a set a set of values named and yes
as you can imagine you're gonna get a
matrix which is you know stuck in all
those columns of all the cues that are
down all the case started at a time and
all the values down Bam Bam Bam Bam
so how many columns you have you have T
columns right because you stuck T
vectors right what is the height of the
vectors
well d right because you we just said
mmm quickly so what next
so before we said that my a was these
soft dark max over the arc max of ha
now you're gonna check one query against
all these keys right so we tilt first
the K such that I have my Rose right tan
tan tan tan and then I multiply my first
row my first key four times my query
second key times the K query
third key blah blah blah right how many
rows I have I have T lowercase T right
so at the end you have T scores and now
you compute the soft dark max and
therefore we get the probability right
hmm I think it makes sense I mean it
makes sense to me I spend a bit of time
but yeah does it make sense to you know
yes what's the difference in Q and K
okay he represents the key which is the
title in the recipe recipe book right q
is gonna be my question I want to make
lasagna and then I check all the titles
of my recipe book like how to make pizza
how to make pasta how to make ravioli
how to make tortellini how to make
pulpit Tony how to make lasagna hey
there you go you get a high score there
you retrieve that one okay cool so I
understand why the query is being
derived the biotransformation of X but I
don't understand why K and V are also
being derived from X there is a value so
in your analog II V would be a video so
why do we derive it from yes it says
you're completely right and so that's
gonna be the next slide but this one is
called self attention so you are
actually doing a retrospective work
you're actually thinking in your head I
want to make lasagna so let me think
even harder what are the recipes I can
make and aha found it then I have my
recipe so everything is my head
and given that my head is X I just have
the three things coming from my head and
this is called self attention right
otherwise if you're a bit more normal
than me
and you just go I get a recipe book
you're gonna get that the question comes
from your ex or your brain right
but then the keys and the values come
from the book right so keys and values
you're gonna get them somewhere else and
there's gonna be the cross attention
right and yeah you check your query
against all those kids and they you're
three of the final thing all right so
what's next next is going to be the fact
that yeah we said a hidden layer is
gonna be my linear combination of these
V's known these V columns that are
making my matrix again weighted by these
coefficients alphas that are inside my a
okay so this is exactly the same as we
have seen before but I just specified
specialized yet specialized those
instead of using all the time X and you
know X transpose I have now keys
Aquarians and values right queries keys
queries that one side and then keys and
by just on the other side um Alfredo
yesterday and lecture you and professor
Lacan says there is only one maybe like
one Curie but multiple you know one
curium multiple keys and value so here
one means there's only one Curie for 1x
I like 1qi current 1x I but it has to
interact all the other keys right right
so exactly that was okay thank you for
reminding me that's so the point here in
this line the last line I show you here
you have one Q in one Q this is one
question how to make lasagna you're
gonna check how these matches all the
titles in the book right so one question
is gonna be going through all the titles
Tata Tata ton in order to find where the
correct title is right it's a one
question how to make lasagna and you
check how to make pizza how to make
pasta how to make tortellini how to make
pulpit on it a name you retrieve the one
that the one that actually matches right
so you have one
you check that our many keys and then
you retrieve the value of the one that
matches or if you actually have two high
scores you can make a mixture of recipes
right and then I don't know how well
that interpolate does it make sense
someone was talking before by two
recipes right so if I check check how to
make lasagna and then in my book I have
lasagna with the e at the end and then I
don't know some other thing that sounds
very similar so maybe if the the word
you're looking for or let me think
another word like let's say I want to
make pizza but then there is another is
a recipe which is called chicken pizza
Allah with Allah is like like with pizza
but like similar with pizza but if I
look for pizza also Pizza Allah is gonna
be having like a higher matching score
right and so if I make pizza if I take
the art max it's gonna work fine if I
take the soft dark max I'm gonna get a
combination between pizza and pizza
Allah because they are similar so you're
gonna get some you know mass probability
mass cameo so in the other guy and then
when you retrieve the values the values
are going to be again the linear
combination of those columns using
multiplied by these coefficients and so
if you have a one hot you're gonna get
just one value but then if there are
multiple values which are you know known
like if you have like a soft dark max
you may have you know several values
that are gonna be mixed together and you
say we got two very close candidates
that has high a value say then it's
pizza and Yola but here my Curie the Q
is only one right so Q is gonna be pizza
but then inside the key there are two
recipes which is pizza and pizza Yola
and these two are very similar so both
of them the score will be somehow
similar right and so whenever you do the
soft arc max you don't exactly get only
one very high score maybe gonna get a
high score and then another high score
so H
is gonna be the linear combination of
these recipes are gonna be like the
average of the pizza and the pizza Ola
got it okay yeah I truly make sense
thank you
of course there was another question no
okay maybe we should move on because we
have 15 minutes left okay again how many
queues do we have we have T Q's right we
have many kills and therefore all hold
on
so what's beta beta we like to set that
to 1 over square root of D why is that
because if you have a vector of all ones
in one dimension the length of a vector
of one has is one in two dimensions the
vector which is all come coordinates one
is going to be square root of 2 a vector
that has all components one in the three
dimension is going to have square root
of three right if you have four
components can be square root of that so
you a vector in D dimension you're gonna
have that the magnitude grows with the
square root of the number of dimensions
and so in order to keep the temperature
constant of these soft arc max we want
to divide by the square root of the
number of dimensions again technicality
doesn't matter if you don't get it again
how many queries we have T and therefore
we can get T AIDS right and therefore we
get a matrix capital a so finally you're
gonna get a big H which is simply the
multiplication of these values by this
matrix of you know where the columns are
going to be the mixing components and it
was pretty much it about cross cross
attention could you just say exactly why
queue and care of the same dimension but
V is their friend I would expect key and
V K and V to be of the same dimension
but Q to be something else
V is gonna be my pizza recipe right it's
gonna be 10 pages long oh no can make
one page long instead Q and K is the
question and the title and they have to
match because I'm gonna
comparing like I'm gonna compare what is
the matching you know degree right how
these two are aligned this comes from
this thing over here right so whenever I
check my query against all keys
I do the roll times vector and they have
to be having the same size the same
length right otherwise I can't multiply
so you check your question against all
these keys you know you get a sports
yeah I think that matrix and then you
get the recipe which can be the whole
YouTube video or meat cooking whatever
right right okay
okay thank you sure anytime
I'm hungry okay okay so one
implementation detail known for example
to make things faster and we can stack
all those doubles in one whole W right
and then BOOM you compare you can you
compute all Q and K and D in one one one
second right in one iteration
nothing fancy Ryan we have done the same
before for the RNN right remember we
were stuck in the X and the H and
computing these with the stock version
of the W reign on the top right hand
side okay so nothing fancy well then
there is something else called heads so
this can represent one head but we may
have multiple heads for example H heads
so if I have h heads I'm gonna have h qs
and I have age case I'm gonna have H B's
and so you're going to end up with a
thing that is going to be H times taller
right but then you can still get it back
to whatever dimension if you multiply at
this big guy at the end now this final
big vector which is gonna be the vector
of the B's right at the end you can
multiply by a matrix to make it back to
this size of D this is a possible way of
implementing this stuff right but again
details not important so let's get
finally to this transformer what the
heck is this transformer so the
originary this transformer is made by
two blocks is a made of
encoder and a decoder okay so where have
we seen before is this encoder decoder
architecture
right in the janitors out encoders there
you go so recap from out encoders right
so out encoders we had the diagram on
the left today we're going to be
focusing the diagram on the right hand
side you have two blocks you have an
encoder and I have a decoder the encoder
Maps the X to the hidden representation
and then the decoder mapped the hidden
representation to these again
input again but we don't have to I mean
we have these two main major components
right in the app out encoder and so in
this case we're gonna have something
similar more or less so this is the
transformer encoder which is the purple
block right so in these guys in this guy
we're gonna have the self attention cool
we already know what it is in the upper
part we're going to be running a
basically a linear layer here every
component so if you think about a
convolutional a convolution with the
kernel size of one you basically apply
the same linear layer to every element
in the in the set right sometimes they
call it this you know feed-forward but
it's going to be a feed-forward applied
to every element in the set so it's
actually a convolution where the
convolutional kernel is equal one then
we apply some module which we can call
this ad and norm both after both of
these guys
what is this module here so this guy is
basically a box here which has two
components has a addition component and
then has a layer normalization okay and
so if we connect this guy here on the
right hand side you're gonna get that
the self attention basically has a
residual connection but like that is
bypassing it and then the layer
normalization and the same happens for
the other guy on top so also the the
convolutional part has these residual
connection and be a layer normalization
so how does it work over all this stuff
you wanna basically put the set of
inputs at the bottom and then you make
it blah blah blah bubble up right and
you get the hidden representation at the
output of the encoder right so this H
encoder
thing fancy right I just put two blocks
we have seen the self attention just
before the one deconvolution us actually
know how it works right is a applying
just you know the single multi-layer
perception to every component in this
set and then normalization helps you
know getting those gradients coming back
later on and the receiver connection
connection makes everything smooth
alright so this was the encoder how do
we how what is the decoder in this case
so let me clean up a little bit so let
me remove first the encoder box let me
remove that old zone Teledyne let me
actually even remove these X on the
bottom and the final out the drain so
this was the encoder but now I'm gonna
delete the connection there in the
center poof okay and so now we're going
to be talking about the decoder so the
decoder is exactly like the encoder but
I'm gonna have a cross attention like
some one of you was mentioning before of
course right they were you were asking
me why the heck are you checking these
keys from yourself so this cross
attention gets connected right after
these normalization module right and of
course cross attention gets these hidden
representation from the last layer of
the encoder and then what else you're
gonna have the same stuff so the
addition and normalization you connect
this stuff and then finally you plug it
back right so we have one extra module
and this is gonna be my decoder right so
the decoder is like the encoder but has
this additional module sandwiched
between these previous between it could
you say more about the cross attention
cross attention is exactly the self
attention but
you have the fact that my keys like this
X here and this guy here are no longer X
but these are gonna be my age from the
encoder right that's it
and coder and this was the set right so
I still like the set of Ages all the
same and whatever
try it with the mouse okay so this is
exactly the same where I just replaced
the X's with the final hidden
representation from the encode array so
that's it this guy here is gonna be
providing me the values and the keys so
we still use the original axis to
compute the query and then you use the
HS to compute the so the this one you're
gonna get these the X to compute the the
the D queries here here I compute the
queries and this one allows me to
compute the K keys and then the values
okay so how does it work how do we train
this stuff right so what we get there on
the bottom from the bottom there we're
gonna have the output these Y hat from
the previous iteration and so you're
gonna get a output there at the output
of the of the system maybe there is like
some additional layer missing there and
then in an autoregressive fashion you're
gonna get this output you feed it back
you know there's some additional layer
on top of it it doesn't matter I mean
it's not important and then you put it
back and then you you know you out
aggressively output a sequence of
outputs right and then every time you
have a new input this new input will ask
for a different query and a different
query is going to be asking about
different values from the encoder right
so the encoder basically summarized what
is the content of my input set right so
before we saw that this guy here yeah so
here we have a input set and then the
output of this guy is going to be a set
of hidden representation and then you
have the decoder is going to be querying
what is required through this cue from
this set of representations from the
encoder okay and we really have to go to
the notebook because otherwise we have
no time left so import stuff whatever so
here we have the multi-head attention
right how does this multi-head attention
work so in the init
part we're gonna have these three
matrices w-qm WK & WV that are allowing
me to rotate my current input right and
then we have this one that is allowing
me to merge together the heads at the
end and so how does this forward works
right so in the forward you're gonna get
a input X for the query and input X for
the keys and an input for the values and
now you have the Q the K and the V are
simply you know the multiplication of my
input for the specific item multiplied
by this matrix WQ right so this is the
rotation of my X and so here you have
the Q K and V then you're going to
compute this scale dot product so we can
go and see this on scale dot product
which are basically the dot product
between the one question against all the
keys so if we go up here I can't even
scroll sorry
let me zoom a little one second okay so
here you get these arrays so here you
get basically the discourse okay first
we divide by the square root of the
dimension because we said before
otherwise stuff starts exploding then we
have a matrix multiplication between one
query against all these keys right and
then at the end we apply the soft dark
max right such that we can compute the
squares they I'm sorry did we can
compute compute the mixing mixing
coefficient right and then finally you
multiply these mixing coefficients with
the V matrix you get basically the final
output right and that was pretty much it
this was the self attention right and
then finally since you have multiple
heads we're going to be squashing
everything together by using this final
WH so that was the first part they
dubbed the attention are there questions
on these attention I mean if you follow
this light this is
exactly the same okay just let me know
if you need me to go slower on this part
then on the bottom part so what do we
need we have the attention part so this
is the self attention right so what what
I what are we trying to do right this is
a multi-headed attention so what are we
trying to do here we are going to be
just using an encoder to classify some
sentences which are sentences described
in some movies has been a positive
review or a negative review so I'm just
gonna be using the encoder and then
train this encoder to perform a
classification task so what do we need
for the encoder the encoder if we check
from these slides so if we check here
what do we need for the encoder the
encoder has two components right there
is the self attention which we just saw
the code and then we had this
convolution right this MLP multi-layer
perceptron applied to every element in
the set so let's figure out where this
convolutional layer is some sanity check
hold on this stuff is gonna be online by
the end of today so there is this
encoder layer and the encoder layer has
this much attention plus the
convolutional net and the convolutional
net you pretty know pretty much know how
it works right so you can actually
figure out if you check the fight' or
documentation that the linear and then
linear acts is a one-dimensional
convolution so you can use you know n n
linear here so this is like a
convolutional net you have a convolution
the real o and then you have the final
convolution okay I think I'm not running
because I think you already know how to
make convolutional net and then we have
the tool layer normalization right so
first you have multi-head attention it's
a self attention so we provide X X and X
for all the inputs right then use a
stupid question but why call it a
convolution at all is it's just a no
okay it's not it's not stupid it's very
important because a linear layer would
be mapping you know some representation
into some other representation
is applied to every component in the set
right so I have a set here right yeah a
set of inputs and over here I'm gonna
have a set of representation right so I
have a set here yeah then I apply the
linear layer to every element separately
okay mm-hmm so if you apply the same
linear layer to every element in a
sequence Oh
Bhushan right okay so everyone could
each each each hidden representation is
going to be M going through the one
contribution separately yeah so in the
in the original paper they call it a
linear layer but it's not because it's
actually a convolution right so again
every every time you're gonna see the
every implementation is gonna use a
linear layer all of them are going to be
calling a feed-forward but are these are
convolution it does some broadcasting
but I can eat a convolution the same way
we call soft arcamax
and we called with I don't call it soft
max because you know it's it's wrong
right okay but it's very good question
I'm almost done I understand okay so
this is my convolutional net and then
you have multi-layer attention and this
CN n right and again this is simply a
one dimensional one dimensional like
it's a one dimensional convolution where
the kernel size is also one right and so
it can be implemented with a linear but
I would write here and then one
deconvolution right with the kernel of
size one actually they are implemented
in exactly the same way in in if you
check the code on Phi torch but this
would be the correct like is a
convolution way all right so you have
the multi lytic Multi multi head
attention you get the first output then
you send this output you sum this to the
input right because we had the residual
connection you send it through the layer
normalization and then you have an
output
so you have an output oh one you send
the output inside the convolution you
get this guy which you're gonna be
bypassing now with a residual connection
and you feed it to the layer
normalization so that's the encoder
right so the encoder puts all that was
the encoder finnaly fit finish something
I didn't mention was that let me go back
here so I'm using this encoder to do
some sentence classification right
and so each there is there is actually a
order now in the in the words if you put
a bag of word this is basically like
acting and working on a bag of words but
if you actually would like to make sense
you'd like to also send an index right
so the first item should also in the set
should have or this was first item so
your house should send information about
what position that item an item takes
okay so so far this encoder in this
transformer and this attention is
completely permutation equivalent right
because we don't have any information
about order but if I'd like to do
classification of sentences maybe make
sense to take an account the order of
words right because you know order my
matter so we can add some kind of
position information but again it's not
important all right so I have my encoder
which is gonna be just having the
embeddings for the input and then it has
several layers of the encoder so over
here I just show you where the become
okay okay so this is just one encoder
but since we are doing deep networks you
can you know you have multiple encoders
after you know deep networks each of
these is an encoder right and coder so
you can stack multiple of these encoders
to make your network more powerful and
so here you have like a list for a
number of layers you attend several
encoders together
then we train this stuff on these IMDB
data set which is basically giving me
the reviews of the of the movie and then
we have to figure out whether it was a
good or a bad movie and pretty much
that's it
so we train these big guy and I just
keep the training loop because it's
gonna be exactly the same train loop we
have seen so many times you get some you
know accuracy at the beginning it's 50
percent because it doesn't know better
and then as you keep training we get up
to some kind of 1992 and we start maybe
overfitting a little bit and this is the
test accuracy which is 83 percent okay
so something you want to really pay
attention is the fact that when you do
sentence classification with a RNN you
have to send it multiple times right you
have to send the first word inside
they've sent the second word then it's a
sequential set of operations instead in
this case these attention mechanism I
show you right now there is no
sequential operation everything is
computed in one go right so in this case
here you get these final age matrix
which is the representational of all the
element in my sentence it's computing
one goal right so there is no more
temporal loop there is no more waiting
time right it's like boom immediately
immediately done right so this allow you
to paralyze so much because this is just
matrix multiplication right so this is
like stupid to paralyze one more thing
to pay attention is that where is it
there is a matrix the a matrix okay this
guy here this is very dangerous right T
is the number of T is the number of
titles right okay and there you go
so my recipe book has thousand recipes
because it's the one thousand I'll free
the recipe book
what's the size of these metrics is a
thousand times a thousand right
1 million dimension is huge
and so you can can see clearly here the
fact that if you have many indexes many
many many keys right this stuff starts
blowing up quickly pretty quickly right
so you have to pay attention about that
and you know there are different ways to
handle this as well for example you can
split it in half and do something up but
again implementation detail so right now
we are 10 minutes after class I am here
for you and answer every kind of
question but I think we managed to go
through the notebook in a ok
manner questions as to questions yes so
in one head in one attention head you
will only use one matrix one weight
matrix each for the query the key and
the value yes yeah I know you stuck all
the final v's together and then you can
squash them back so at the end I may
have H V then I can use this matrix here
to squash down everything to D dimension
this is a way of doing this ok ok so
multi descent multi-headed attention
essentially is just using multiple
weight matrices that don't share that
yeah something happened in the between
by yes the the multi-headed attention
means you have multiple queries for the
same input right and then allows you to
have multiple questions about the same
wheel like you're hungry so one question
would be how can I make lasagna but you
know that you don't have ground beef at
home
so a second question would be mmm can I
do a vegetarian dish and so you know
given that you're still hungry you may
have different questions your mind
okay and can you go to the slide with
the encoder/decoder structure that used
cross attention yeah sure here okay so
the input to the first self attention
layer would be the way you calculate the
query in that case would be W Q times X
I say Q I will be called attack so in
this in the self attention right yeah so
in the self attention all those are hold
on those q qk and V are coming from the
Y hat right instead of X you want to
replace this X with Y hat right
so what was that again what was the
white hat again Y hat is gonna be my so
whenever you train this system here
you're gonna be predicting the first
word okay aha I didn't even tell you
you're you're right
so this system is trained to do
translation you put a sentence in input
in a one language I'm happy hungry I'm
hungry and then you put the other
language like in Italian for example or
famine and you want to make you know you
feed here and I'm hangry
and it's gonna be the representation of
the I'm hungry hungry not hungry I'm
hungry in English and then after you
feed you put here I'm hungry the first
word you're gonna be outputting is gonna
be here in Inked in Italian oh and if I
you put all down here you enforce the
system to put family as output which is
hungry in Italian so if I say okay let
me let me put a minute write down maybe
if I want to say okay so it's so it's a
cut yeah so let's say a cut in English
and then you have in Italian oh god oh
god got oh okay so first you have a cut
that goes inside the encoder and then
the encoder spits this guy here and
there is one H associated to each of
these inputs and then these if you put
this stuff inside here at the beginning
you're going to
a big zero here and this stuff is gonna
spit out a one which is the a now you
put the one down here and then this guy
is gonna be spitting out got oh they put
got to inciting us in this guy this
guy's gonna say finish that's it it will
go to the end right II yes okay every
time you get a different input here at
the bottom the decoder can decide to
look at different components of these
eight encoder okay that doesn't make
sense yes and what's going to the class
attention module in that case the cross
attention module is getting the output
this wire here is the output of this add
norm so the output of this add norm goes
inside the heater for the Q the the
query in the cross attention and then is
getting this guy here the the values and
the the keys from the you know the
encoder okay thanks okay there were take
questions you said the first was about
how many matrices you'd use for a single
thank you sure of course
I hope it was a bit more clear than
yesterday but again I noticed there is a
lot of it was pretty dense today class I
hope like I was just confused about what
the cells refer to and what the cross
referred yeah yeah yeah more questions
in this example of the cat on gato mum
so you said out of the decoder you get
some representation and you pass that
back into as a why so to me that looks
like like some kind of recurrence is it
not this is this is called auto
regressive
right so this is for generating text and
so to generate text you have to generate
the first output now you feed the
and that output inside you're gonna get
the second guy right so the encoder
doesn't have any auto regressive thing
yeah the encoder just generates this H
encoder then the decoder is gonna be
generating one word at a time in an
autoregressive fashion so the right guy
is a generative model right
but d-train the encoder and decoder at
all at once when you're training this
model yeah so how does it how do you
train it if it's auto regressive and one
step depends on the previous step your
sentence when you're doing inference is
auto regressive oh so inference is auto
regressive but training is yeah because
you have the wrong ones
okay you just mask the future time step
so that you don't show it if you're
trying to do it for the first word it
receives only the first not everything
else and so on
let's call like a look ahead mask okay
Jesus thanks I'm just going with your
examples from earlier with this the cat
and we were saying to cue in this case
would be like an Italian word right I
like pudding the second time around and
one top right right right and then it
comes down and then we feed it through
and it the cue goes into the cross
attention and at that point K is gonna
be the key for the English the encoded
English word but then the value is also
gonna be from the English representation
right so how does that end up spitting
out like an Italian word good question
you stuck multiple of these modules and
somehow the magic happens I don't know
the values and the keys are coming from
the English but again this okay so
whenever you train this system you will
end up with representations that are
basically language agnostic I would
assume therefore you have on one side
English the other side Italian
but in the middle part whenever you have
these kind of embeddings we can assume
this to be like language agnostic right
and so the question is gonna just figure
out hey this Italian word is looking for
something that looks like this what are
the encoding what are the embeddings
here that are you know matching my
specific question right now okay so I
think that could be like an
interpretation I guess so you have
Italian down English down here and as
you bubble up the encoder you remove the
language specificity and then you kind
of reuse this kind of you know encoders
I guess I mean this is similar to how it
works in the encoder decoder recurrent
neural network you have an encoder which
is encoding one whole sentence and then
you can have like a representation of
that sentence that doesn't depend on the
language anymore right
and then actually after having the
recurrent Network you used to have a
dick like a decoder which is or just
using that final representation or you
can also have an attention which is
looking at specific I think time steps
in the in the past so it's it's part of
the language the natural neural language
translation NTM brain neural language
and nltc machine machine translation and
it that yeah that's part of that kind of
stuff sorry so just last question
somewhat did I answer your question
before I mean this is my guess right
it's like that the embedding is gonna be
the day H H encoder are like they are
stripping off the the language specific
information they are just concepts right
they are just the the representation of
the concept without the language
attached there you go that would be my
it sounds like thank you in a sense it's
gonna be an embedding that's in itself
so it's and then that's going to be
compared with the K that's correct and
the Q in this case comes from your
language that is gonna be the target
language right
right okay make sense
thank you I would really recommend
having a look to the blog from my friend
which is called illustrated transformer
it's very very very nicely written and
it's a bit maybe it has a bit more
context about the the language part I
try to do you know I try not to have the
language inside this presentation
because you know you can use this
transformer for any kind of data right
and basically these are mapping sets to
sets but again maybe this example here
was just you know very tailored to the
translation part but translation you can
also have like transformers for making
generative models pixel by pixel so you
can actually draw things with this thing
with this architecture is very
transformed by J Alomar yeah yeah him
okay
yeah I really I really like the way he
sees things but here's all my matrices
transposed so that is like bugging me I
think I'm the one who transposed the
matrices everyone has them horizontal I
I think it was the math was nicer with a
vertical okay more questions you said
that the encoded representations would
be language agnostic doesn't that assume
some sort of similarity in the way that
I'm in both the languages you're
translating to and strong like as
language is like for example something
that case for the representations to be
language agnostic you have the same
between English and English in French
there's more of a similarity then say
English and Chinese not just with
respect to the kind of data that's
available but also the combat experience
reports of the languages so does this
work as well across languages languages
that aren't as similar or does it how
much worse does it perform does it work
as well you know any sorts languages or
like languages which are not very
similar is a problem for any any model
like and of course on something
I should that can solve it so I don't
think it's it's going to attack that
problem what all classes of models have
issues with like when the target and
source language is a very different his
Libyan work surrounding trying to bridge
that gap just out of curiosity and yes
but like it's an open problem for sure
okay
more questions for me or for Australia
language question for hair and content
maybe questions for me um Carol again
asked about encoder and decoder that
could we go back to the page yeah thank
you so I understand cross attention is
we have attention with the encoder you
know States I'm a bit confused about the
self attention part so here self
attention only happens in why because we
couldn't see the words in the future
right so when I input like when I'm in
time T then the sava would the self
attention to does it do attention amount
order why that hat although why that is
before the time sake so we had to
specify actually I think I'd done a poor
job explaining here so there are two
parts of this the first is training and
in training you have the whole sequence
but then of course you can't look at the
future output right so the first why
here at the bottom you cannot look at
the second why right and the second why
cannot look at the third and so like the
first one cannot look at the whole
future wise but the future wise can look
at the previous wise right because you
can always know what you are gonna be
outputting but you cannot know what you
might output in the future so whenever
you train this system you also need to
somehow mask the future information that
you're providing to the system and so
here you're gonna have the whole set
going in this basically first module of
the end of the decoder generates the
questions and the questions come down
here are going to be retrieving the
information from the encoded sentence
and
and is encoded sentence somehow gets
converted into the other language and
then this is done all in one pass boom
whenever you actually do inference in
this case you're gonna have you
basically start with a specific
representation from the encoder you get
no initial value so you get like a zero
maybe and then you you're gonna ask an
old question what is gonna be the first
word I should start with and then this
one's gonna tell you all you should
start with the translation of a maybe
right so you go end up with a una una
and and then you go you place this on
down to the input and so given that now
the network knows that oh I already
outputted one then what is gonna be the
next question is going to be all alone
listen what's gonna be my next word
after I have inputted une and this is my
second question right the second
question is going to retrieve or you
should talk about the cut and the cut is
this representation and is this cut
representation gets therefore converted
here into the corresponding gato that is
you know cat in Italian and then you put
cut gato back here and then same process
is gonna say oh you reach the end of the
sentence you have like period at the end
we get all have attention with own when
Godot is the second word you can see
everything at all time steps before so
when they see it it means they can have
like attention yes yes it is overall
time steps before the like a builder
current actor internship okay okay thank
you
and I would recommend to watch those
animations from the Distilled dot pub
they have like an article about the
attention and they show you how each
word looks at different specific other
words like if you want to say I couldn't
fit my I couldn't fit my trophy in my
suitcase because it was too large I
guess is the trophy was too large so it
wasn't fitting but if you
say my trophy wasn't couldn't fit in my
luggage because it was too small then
the small is gonna be attending now to
the luggage right because it was too
small then you actually can fit it and
so if you check for example like the
sentence is actually the same the small
or large are both adjectives but one
objective we look at the trophy and the
other objective we look at the luggage
or the suitcase and so again I would
recommend watching the check-in this
distilled out pub article where they
actually give you some nice visuals
about how these attention checks
different parts of a sentence and these
are called something fancy maybe a Shia
knows these sentences I forgot well you
guys give my channel yeah yeah there you
go
II know grad schemes and these are like
do you mind sending that link or at
least directing us what is it called D
still dot pub yeah B still dot tu b
that's from my friend Chris Christopher
Ola he used to be a Google brain now
he's at the open eye eye and he's he's
basically sponsoring himself this
website which is actually basically a
online journal where you have very cute
visualizations right so I make videos
and presentation he makes you know
interactive articles and yeah I really
recommend reading everything from there
I really like it yeah I have nice
friends on the internet more questions I
think this should have been spread
across two lessons to split the dance
I'm sorry do you have any idea about
what the reformer network does yeah so
you can actually check the reformer
Network on author blog post I forgot
them deal with longer sequences because
like the current ones were are not able
to deal with like more than 512 for
example but but yeah they do some fancy
LSH attention I don't know like it was
the back of my hand and the problem with
having those long sequences is this
alright so this one blows
right there is a again there is a blog
post from a girl I forgot her name
Lillian Lillian Lillian has a nice blog
post from two days ago or three days ago
which is called a transformer family
okay there are some errors in the blog
post but ok I think it's good more
questions or I'm gonna be cooking dinner
sorry I could you just say one more time
that they titled the article from this
table pub so the Bastille a pub let me
check I actually don't know exactly
okay this is Jay supercool guy and the
article he actually I didn't write so
this should be coming from the Distilled
dot pub if I'm not mistaken so the thing
I was referring is this one okay this
this illustration these pictures from
this Illustrated transformer and I
believe this is coming from the
distilled of pub from a Christopher Ola
so the other website is the still dot
pub yeah there we go so here you have
the attention sequence modeling
[Music]
attention they're gone I think this I
think it's coming from here
[Music]
it talks about the heart attention and
soft attention I think okay maybe I lied
I was talking about these pictures here
okay so I thought this was coming from
this table pub that maybe I was mistaken
these are the pictures that was talking
like the their name they attend to
different words okay okay the animal
didn't cross the street because it was
too tired and then you have here that it
was the only more atom anima right but
then it was - maybe the animal didn't
cross the street because it was too wide
in this case white instead of tired
should be you know attending to street
in this case right both it can be street
and animal but you know you have higher
scores here right so the scalar product
is a has a higher score in this region
here right you need anything from me
more
no nope okay right
what why nice seeing you and nice
talking to you so we are done now it was
quite a substantial lesson right so
again how can you get more out of these
lessons
so again comprehension something was not
clear I've done a poor job just then ask
me anything in the comment section below
news you can find everything about what
I'm doing and what I'm teaching on
Twitter at the FCN said handle updates
again if you subscribe to this YouTube
channel you're gonna have the latest
videos as soon as I upload them online
if you like my work and this video in
particular just press the like button
this video has an English transcript you
can find in the course website where all
the titles are linked to the sections of
this video
parla Italiano hablas espanol new Ohama
you speak Korean you speak Turkish we
have all these translations now
available on the course website so go
out there and check it out
if you'd like to have your own language
available as well feel free to contact
me such that we can get started with the
translation part and finally you should
try to go over the piperj
notebook we have core in this class and
make yourself familiar with all the
methods and classes and all the little
things you should try to train this
notebook change parameters such that you
can get you know some good understanding
of what it was all about okay it was
quite a lot this time so you'd better
check out this notebook right and
finally if you find errors typos and you
know everything you think I can do
better we can do better we can improve
the content with your help if you
contribute to the github repository
where the website is hosted and that was
pretty much it again thank you so much
for sticking around with us and bye-bye